A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Finance, Vice President, Office Files of Roger G. Kennedy FA581
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Finance, Vice President, Office Files of Roger G. Kennedy
1969-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kennedy, Roger G.
Ford Foundation
FA581
2.66 Cubic Feet 7 Hollinger document boxes
Roger G. Kennedy joined the Ford Foundation in 1970 as Vice President of the Office of Finance. Charged with steering the Foundation towards achieving long-term sustainability despite the high inflation of the 1970s, he restructured the expenditures, investment strategies, and portfolio. He also served as a key advisor on financial matters to President McGeorge Bundy and to the Board of Trustees Finance Committee, and frequently prepared dockets and presented reports and recommendations to the Committee. The Finance Committee, initiated by the Board of Trustees in 1953, set investment policy and monitored the performance of the Foundation's portfolio. The Office Files of Roger G. Kennedy span from 1969 to 1979 and consist of memoranda, reports, articles, speeches, background and meeting materials documenting his work as Vice President of the Office of Finance (1969-1977) and later as Vice President of the Office of the Arts (1978-1979). The bulk of the collection consists of Finance Committee dockets. These dockets contain agenda books (later called "Treasurer's Reports") with portfolio reviews and summaries of investment holdings. Also part of Mr. Kennedy's Committee records are memoranda and correspondence pertaining to the Foundation's efforts to divest and diversify its portfolio of Ford Motor Company stock. Other files contain research memoranda and recommendations by investment research staff within the Office of Finance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Custodial History
This collection consists of files removed by Mr. Kennedy when he left the Foundation and then returned in April 2011. Mr. Kennedy donated other papers to the Smithsonian Institution, where he had served as Director of its National Museum of American History from 1979 to 1992.
The records created by the Office of the Treasurer's staff originally were not part of Mr. Kennedy's files. The decision to incorporate them into the collection was made during processing.
Arrangement
Arranged into 4 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Finance Committee Records, 1969-1977
Series II. Office of the Arts Files, 1977-1979
Series III. Speeches and Writings, 1971-1976
Series IV. Investment Research Files, 1969-1973
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Roger G. Kennedy span from 1969 to 1979 and consist of memoranda, reports, articles, speeches, background and meeting materials documenting his work as Vice President of the Office of Finance (1969-1977) and the Office of the Arts (1978-1979).
The bulk of the collection consists of Finance Committee dockets. These dockets contain agenda books (later called "Treasurer's Reports") with portfolio reviews and summaries of investment holdings. The files also hold meeting minutes, reports and background memoranda, and proposed By-Laws amendments. Mr. Kennedy was responsible for preparing and distributing briefing materials about investment activities to Committee members for review in advance of meetings. The Tax Reform Act of 1969 also led the Foundation to amend its By-Laws to expand the powers and duties of the Vice President of Financial Affairs and the Treasurer and enable them to manage the Foundation's assets independently from the Board.
There are also memoranda discussing proposed new agreements between the Ford Motor Company and the Foundation regarding the sale and conversion of Ford Motor Company non-voting Class A stock. Other memoranda discuss the terms for continued use of external advisors to manage portions of the Foundation's investments.
Also part of Mr. Kennedy's Committee records are memoranda and correspondence pertaining to the Foundation's efforts to divest and diversify its portfolio of Ford Motor Company stock. There also is correspondence between Mr. Kennedy and then-President McGeorge Bundy regarding the Foundation's financial affairs.
Other files contain research memoranda and recommendations by investment research staff within the Office of the Treasurer.
Biographical / Historical
Roger G. Kennedy was born in St. Paul, Minnesota in 1926. He received a B.A. from Yale University in 1949 and a law degree from the University of Minnesota. During the 1950s, he served as Special Assistant to the U.S. Attorney General; the U.S. Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare; and the U.S. Secretary of Labor. He began a career in banking during the 1960s, serving as Chairman of the Executive Committee of the Northwestern Bank of St. Paul, Minnesota and as Vice President of Investments at the University of Minnesota.
Mr. Kennedy joined the Ford Foundation in 1970 as Vice President of the Office of Finance. Charged with steering the Foundation towards achieving long-term sustainability despite the high inflation of the 1970s, he restructured expenditures and the investment portfolio. He also served as a key advisor on financial matters to President McGeorge Bundy and to the Board of Trustees' Finance Committee, and frequently prepared dockets and presented reports and recommendations to the Committee. The Finance Committee, initiated by the Board of Trustees in 1953, set investment policy and monitored the performance of the Foundation's portfolio. Finance Committee members during Mr. Kennedy's tenure included Stephen D. Bechtel, McGeorge Bundy, William H. Donaldson, John H. Loudon, J. Irwin Miller, Julius A. Stratton, and Bethuel M. Webster.
In 1978, Mr. Kennedy became Vice President of the newly created Office of the Arts (formerly Office of Humanities and the Arts). While in office, he drafted several reports assessing the field of grant-making in the arts and identified opportunities and possible focuses for grant-making. He also was involved with the Forty-Second Street Development Corporation and its efforts to revitalize the small theatre district of West 42nd Street.
Mr. Kennedy departed the Foundation in 1979 to become Director of the Smithsonian's National Museum of American History. From 1993 to 1997, he served as Director of the National Parks Service. He has also taught at Harvard, Yale and Stanford University.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Office of Finance, established in 1970, continued and expanded upon the functions of the Office of the Treasurer (1966-1970), the Office of the Treasury (1958-1966), and the Treasurer (prior to 1958). Its creation and mandate were shaped by the need for the Foundation to respond to two major financial developments. The first was passage of the Tax Reform Act of 1969, which increased federal scrutiny of the expenditure of all charities. The second was the threat that high rates of inflation and an unstable economy posed to the Foundation's assets and grant-making. The Office of Finance initiated stricter and more formalized procedures to guide the Foundation through this period of immense financial and economic change and uncertainty.
The Foundation's Board of Trustees' Finance Committee amended the By-Laws in 1970. The new amendments gave the Vice President of Finance and the Treasurer, acting jointly, sole power to buy and sell the Foundation's stock, bonds, and real estate assets. The Office of Finance retained an internal investment research staff to assist with the reshaping and diversification of the Foundation's investment portfolio.
The Office of the Arts originated as the Office of Humanities and the Arts, created in 1957 under the direction of its first Vice President, W. McNeil Lowry. In 1979, the Office of the Arts was restructured as a program area under Education and Public Policy and, after another reorganization in 1997, it became part of Education, Media, Arts and Culture. Education, Media, Arts and Culture was reorganized as the Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom Program in 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Completion of a use agreement is required prior to providing scholarly access. See RAC Head of Reference (or applicable designee) for details.
- Finance Committee Records, 1969-1977; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of agenda books, minutes, memoranda, Treasurer's Reports and briefing materials for quarterly Finance Committee meetings between 1970 and 1977. The briefing materials varied from meeting to meeting but held information about proposed amendments to the Foundation's By-Laws (1970), accountings of expenditures drawn from the General Reserve, and reviews of the Foundation's direct placement policy and portfolio. There are also memoranda regarding the sale and conversion of Ford Motor Company non-voting Class A stock and the terms for continued use of external advisors.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged chronologically.
  - Bundy, McGeorge -- Memoranda Re: Structure of Present Financial System, Financial Reorganization, Portfolio Diversification, etc., 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ford Motor Company -- Memoranda Re: Ford Bond Sales and Diversification of Stock, 1970 August-1973 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Special Meeting (1 of 2), 1970 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Special Meeting (2 of 2), 1970 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1970 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report -- "Income and Expenditure Expectations and Their Budgetary Implications", 1970 September (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report -- "A Prejudice Paper Revisited", 1970 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Agenda Book (1 of 2), 1970 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting (2 of 2), 1970 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1971 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report -- "Budget Plans and Problems: FY 1972 and 1973", 1971 March (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Report -- "Statement of Investment Policies and Guidelines", 1971 March (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1971 June 23 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Report -- "How to Protect the Portfolio Against Inflation", 1971 September (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Report -- "Social Considerations and the Investment Process" (with McGeorge Bundy comments on draft), 1971 September 21-November (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1971 December 9 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Report -- "Planning for the Foundation's Program in 1973 and Beyond", 1972 March (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1972 June 21 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1972 September 27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Agenda Book, Background Materials for Meeting, 1972 December 8 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Report -- "Preliminary Budget Planning for FY 1974 and FY 1975", 1973 March (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1973 December 13 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Budget -- Memoranda Re: Recommendations, Papers on Ford Foundation Budgetary Quandary, Background on Interest Rates, Stock Values, etc., 1974 March-April (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Proxy Committee -- Memoranda Re: Recommendations for Action, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Report -- "The Ford Foundation Real Estate Investment Program 1974 Supplement", 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Report -- "Our Finances and Our Future", 1974 September (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Report -- "Choices Under a Reduced Program Budget", 1974 November (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1974 December 12 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1975 March 25 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Report -- "Real Estate Portfolio Review for the Finance Committee of the Ford Foundation", 1975 March (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Memoranda Re: Cost Reduction and Investment Recommendations, 1975 June (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Report -- "On Managing Risk", 1975 September (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1975 December 15 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1976 March (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Finance Committee Meeting/Board of Trustees Meeting -- Memoranda for Trustees, Quarterly Investment Report, etc., 1976 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Report -- "Budget Policy, Investment Policy, Prudence and Risk", 1976 July (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1976 September (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Background Materials for Meeting, 1976 December 9 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Finance Committee Meeting -- Agenda, Background Materials for Meeting, 1977 March 23 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report -- "Investment Policies, Spending Policies and Uncertainty", 1977 June (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Office of the Arts Files, 1977-1979; II
  This series consists of three files that describe activities of the Office of the Arts during Mr. Kennedy's tenure as Vice President. One file contains correspondence, memoranda and clippings about the Forty-Second Street Development Corporation and the role of the Foundation in the redevelopment of West 42nd Street and Theatre Row between 1978 and 1979. The other two files contain reports, "Why Bother about the Arts?" (March 1977), which reviews grant-making in the arts generally and makes a case for areas of focus, and "The Arts Office: A Two-Year Report," prepared by Mr. Kennedy for the November 1978 meeting of the Board of Trustees Arts Committee.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Report -- "Why Bother About the Arts?", 1977 March (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Report -- "The Arts Office: A Two-Year Report", 1978 November (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Forty Second Street Local Development Corporation -- Memoranda and Clippings on Times Square Redevelopment, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Speeches and Writings, 1971-1976; III
  This series consists of copies of Mr. Kennedy's speeches and writings on such topics as investment performance measurement; portfolio management, social responsibility, and philanthropy; and the effects of inflation.
  - Talk on Corporate Responsibility Given Before Institutional Investor Conference Group, Washington, DC, 1971 May 13 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Some Suggested Language for Bill Donaldson for His Speech to the Teachers Group" (draft), 1971 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Barker Et Al Revisited" (comments on Robert R. Barker's "Managing Educational Endowment"), 1973 July 4 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "The Uses and Abuses of Performance Measurement" (drafts and submission to Institutional Investor), 1973 July 18-November 11 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Statement Before U.S. Senate Finance Committee Subcommittee on Financial Markets, 1973 September 27 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Wages of Inflation," The Atlantic, 1974 September (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Speech on Disparate Reflections on Portfolio Management, Philanthropy and State of the World Given to Minnesota Council on Foundations, 1977 April (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "Portfolio Decisions and Social Responsibility," Paper for 1974-1975 Lecture Series on Contemporary Business Problems, New York University, 1974 November 7 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "On the Behavior of Retorts, Stills, and Trickle-Stills," Reprinted from Harvard Business Review, 1976 March-April (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Article on Managing Ford Foundation Portfolio, Risks, and Budget, Journal of Portfolio Management, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "A Forecast About Forecasting," Reworking of Speech Submitted to New York Times, 1976 October (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Speech Given at Opening of Exhibit from Northwest Architectural Archives, University of Minnesota Special Collections, 1976 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Investment Research Files, 1969-1973; IV
  This series consists of the research the Office of Finance intended to shape Foundation investment decisions. The reports and recommendations are based on monitoring and analysis of the performance of companies and stocks. Lilia Clemente's files constitute the bulk of the series but research by other members of the investment staff Robert P. Bergin, Leo Bessera, Penney P. Burnett, Ruth S. Gamble, Curt W. Livingston, Ronn K. Lytle, Robert J. Powers, and Frank J. Prezelski is also included.
  Arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Bergin, Robert P. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1970 January-1971 September (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Bessera, Leo -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1970 January-1971 September (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Burnett, Penney P. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1969 June-1971 September (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1970 January-December (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1971 January-May (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1971 June-September (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1971 October-December (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1972 January-February (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1972 March-April (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1972 May-June (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1972 July-October (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1972 November-1973 February (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1973 March-April (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1973 May-June (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1973 June-July (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Clemente, Lilia -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1973 August-September (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Gamble, Ruth S. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1971 August-1972 September (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Livingston, Curtis W. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1970 December-1971 June (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lytle, Ronn K. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1970 December-1971 September (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Powers, Robert J. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1971 August-September (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Prezelski, Frank J. -- Investment Research Memoranda and Recommendations, 1970 November-1971 September (Box 7, Folder 8)